<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-10T14:46:14+07:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ray’s blog</title><subtitle>my personal blog
</subtitle><author><name>raidendy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Why I Day Dreaming A Lot Without Realizing It</title><link href="/why-i-day-dreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Day Dreaming A Lot Without Realizing It" /><published>2025-08-10T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>/why-i-day-dreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="/why-i-day-dreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it.html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to discuss my tendency toward introversion and intuition, and how these traits influence the way my mind works. Recently, I have discovered that I daydream a lot, and I think this is related to these aspects of my personality.</p>

<p>I have taken personality tests from MBTI websites such as 16personalities.com, paid tests like the Big Five Traits from Jordan Peterson’s understandmyself.com, and even a DNA test report. All of these tests, including repeated ones over the years, consistently indicate that I’m an INTJ, which stands for Introvert, Intuition, Thinking, and Judging (with a particular focus on introversion and intuition). This also aligns with specific traits in my genes that suggest I am introverted and have strong intuition, such as ‘Introversion’, ‘Insightfulness’, ‘Creativity’, and ‘Trading’, which are rated above average, while other traits like ‘Imagination’ are labeled as Outstanding.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: While MBTI is very questionable personality test and people sometimes use it to stretched into something like Zodiac. Nevertheless, I think it is good when we try to discuss specific traits using Carl Jung Personality Theory.</em></p>

<p>Introvert people is someone who dont get their energy from the external factor like Extrovert people (in a very limited definition).  It means that Introvert undervalue the thing outside of themself, which is what makes the introvert has a tendency toward more valuing internal factor of things, which is themself.</p>

<p>According to Carl Jung, someone with intuition perceives information unconsciously, often through patterns and possibilities that are not readily apparent to the senses or conscious thought. This means having the ability to predict or sense things beyond immediate reality.</p>

<p>In order to describe Introvert Intuition (Ni), we should also describe what is Sensing Extrovert (Se):</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Ni as a dominant function will lead the user to prioritize observing and taking in information, ultimately leading them to create an impression based off of this information. When making these observations, they won’t use details directly, rather they will try to look past the details themselves to see what the pattern structure is that the details are fitting into. This is one reason why Ni users tend to not remember a bunch of specific details, but rather the patterns that emerge as a result of the presented information. They want to be able to recognize certain markers to help them derive the sequence of events that are about to unfold, based on their internal database of past impressions. Because of this, they will prefer to observe first before taking any kind of action. They will want to forecast how things will play out before making a decision or acting. Because their extraverted function is in service to their dominant Ni, having some kind of structured decision will be secondary to making observations for the sake of collecting information.

Having Se as a lead function typically gives the user the urge to interact with the present current world around them. They are prone to boredom if they are forced to spend long periods of time theorizing or planning with no foreseeable way to act on the plans being made. These types are particularly drawn to act of doing and will have a desire to interact with whatever they are faced with in order to learn about it. When problem solving, Se dominants’ first instinct will be to play with the different options available to them in order to see what each thing does in order to form some kind of solution. These types will want to see how things physically change and will use that feedback to in order to inform their next move. While it’s not always extremely prominent, these types tend toward the mindset of living in the moment.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Source: <a href="https://practicaltyping.com/2021/10/25/the-functions-in-each-position-se-ni-ni-se/">Practical Typing</a></p>

<p>These functions of personality can be found in everyone else. Everyone can use it or have ability to use it. But for a certain people, it is how their mind usually works, and they more likely to think in their natural function, and not really familiar to use the other sense of their opposite function which in this case is Se.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Ni sees a web of information in their head so to speak. And their intuition helps them puzzle all pieces of the web together, narrowing down onto just one conclusion/idea. They live a lot in their heads, mulling over their ideas/conclusions. 

Se takes in information as it comes, day happens to them - Present focused (what is most relevant in that moment) - show someone else an experience - liking lots of stimulation and variety
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/mbti/comments/11e1x44/whats_the_difference_between_ne_and_ni/">Reddit</a></p>

<p>These two personality functions can be found in everyone. Everyone can use them or has the ability to use them. But for certain people, this is how their mind usually works, they are more likely to think according to their natural function and are not as familiar using the opposite function, which in this case is extroversion and sensing.</p>

<p>I often find myself daydreaming at work, while commuting, and while riding. It is not the same as thinking; thinking is different from daydreaming (although sometimes we mix the two). Daydreaming is like living inside your head and staying there. Sometimes I forget what reality is, which is why, after all this time, I didn’t realize I was daydreaming, because I can’t see the difference between my inner and outer realities. My mind constantly provides a stream of images and voices that emerge from within, blending with my perception of external reality.</p>

<p>When I read Carl Jung’s theory and people’s writings about Ni types, it made me realize why I do what I do, and how unaware I was for confusing my inner reality with the external world. This confusion has limited my perspective on both.</p>

<p>Obviously, daydreaming has its benefits, such as helping me pass the time, brainstorm, and solve problems when combined with thinking. However, it can also be detrimental, as detachment from external reality and underuse of the sensing function can hinder tasks that require intellectual engagement with sensory input, like using my eyes and hands to solve problems. This means I often lack the external data my mind needs to make accurate predictions or find answers.</p>

<p>This also explains why I’m better at recognizing patterns than remembering specific details. I tend to think about which puzzle piece might fit based on its general shape, rather than focusing on the finer details to make a match. My approach is to move from abstract concepts to details, rather than from details to abstraction—more deductive than inductive. This has been a challenge for me.</p>

<p>But this realization is also a blessing. I now understand that I tend to undervalue my external traits, such as sensing and extroversion. Sometimes I don’t pay much attention to my body or to what others think, because I primarily value my inner voice over external opinions. This is also why I often seem indifferent or lack the motivation to share my thoughts and experiences with others.</p>

<p>From this I also understand that why I choose to work as a legal especially a legal corporate which make sense, given my tendency to incline toward internal side of things. I tend to focus on specific areas that I enjoy most, such as connecting ideas and finding patterns like linking concepts in both law and programming. This is why I’m interested in bridging legal work and technology by developing specialized tools for the legal field. Similarly, in football, my favorite position is Defensive Midfielder (CDM), because it involves connecting and supporting different parts of the team, rather than just attacking or defending.</p>

<p>I also understand why I enjoy long term projects that each smaller task connects to a larger goal, and I appreciate seeing how different projects interrelate. I genuinely enjoy immersing myself in complex problems and staying engaged with them over time.</p>

<p>But here’s the catch: people who are dominant in Ni often face a common problem, their Se function tends to be underdeveloped:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Inferior Se is also playing into this type’s desire to look past the immediate details because the sensory in the present moment is being devalued. This also leads to their tendency to hesitate and not want to act immediately. Their lack of being present in the moment hinders their ability to react immediately and causes them to struggle with improvising. Things not going according to how they foresaw will very likely lead to them being disoriented and unsure of how to proceed. Inferior Se being exercised may lead these types to overindulge in some form of physical pleasure, like food, if not being properly regulated. In a more positive light, it will give these types a desire to travel or otherwise explore the sensory world around them. However, they will want to do so in a planned out and regulated manner as to not get overwhelmed.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Source: <a href="https://practicaltyping.com/2021/10/25/the-functions-in-each-position-se-ni-ni-se/">Practical Typing</a></p>

<p>This means that if I can use my sensory function more, it will enhance my intuition, because the data gathered from sensory experiences will complement what my intuition produces. By integrating external information with my inner reality, my intuition can function more fully.</p>

<p>Jung suggests that each person’s task is to learn the other side of themselves or in this case my opposite function which is sensing and to be more extroverted, to balance out my natural function and develop what is lacking inside of me.</p>

<p>By coming to this realization, I understand my natural strengths and how I can develop them further. I should strive to truly observe what I see, listen to what I hear, and perceive things as they are.</p>

<p>This new perspective will strengthen the dominant function of myself and enrich my internal world with vivid mental images formed during daydreaming. For example, Kim Jung Gi, a Korean artist, spent his childhood observing and drawing extensively, which allowed him to create entire artworks from memory alone. He is an excellent example of someone with dominant Ni who has also mastered his Se function.</p>

<p><em>Watch materials</em>:</p>

<p>you should watch this if you are recongnize as a Ni:</p>

<p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i8o30eArkQA
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DLANmpd-YFc
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DmqFbgKWoao</p>]]></content><author><name>raidendy</name></author><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I want to discuss my tendency toward introversion and intuition, and how these traits influence the way my mind works. Recently, I have discovered that I daydream a lot, and I think this is related to these aspects of my personality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mengukur Potensi Kecerdasan Buatan Pada Bidang Hukum</title><link href="/mengukur-potensi-kecerdasan-buatan-pada-bidang-hukum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mengukur Potensi Kecerdasan Buatan Pada Bidang Hukum" /><published>2022-02-04T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2022-02-04T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>/mengukur-potensi-kecerdasan-buatan-pada-bidang-hukum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/mengukur-potensi-kecerdasan-buatan-pada-bidang-hukum.html"><![CDATA[## Hukum yang tertinggal

Sejauh perkembangan teknologi di abad ini, mulai dari bidang ekonomi, sosial, biologi, fisika, kedokteran, dan antariksa serta bidang keilmuwan lainnya. Namun terdapat bidang yang masih belum beranjak ketahap berikutnya dan kerap kali _old fashioned_ yakni salah satunya adalah bidang __hukum__. Pertanyaannya mengapa demikian?

Kita dapat melihat bagaimana perekonomian sangat disokong oleh teknologi dengan meningkatnya efisiensi pabrik dan industri dalam penggunaan robot dan komputerisasi; Kemudian kehidupan manusia yang sulit terlepas dari teknologi internet dan sosial media; Penemuan antibiotik, vaksin dan teknologi kedokteran, memungkinkan terjadinya peningkatan standar usia manusia secara general; Penerbangan robot ke mars, dan Roket antariksa yang dapat digunakan kembali, memungkinkan peluang kolonisasi manusia di Mars. Namun dengan semua perkembangan teknologi, hukum jauh dari modernitas tersebut.

Kondisi sistem hukum dewasa ini, mulai dari proses pembuatan hukum hingga peradilan dan penegakannya, masih berjalan selayaknya sistem hukum yang dijalankan pada abad 19. Belum ada suatu perkembangan teknologi signifikan dalam peningkatan sistem hukum menuju tahap berikutnya.

## Apakah kita memerlukan itu semua?

Sebagai manusia, kemajuan akan menjadi titik penentuan meningkatnya kebahagian. Dalam pandangan hedonis dan utilitaran, kebahagiaan selalu menjadi pilihan utama dalam menentukan keputusan dan cara hidup demi mengurangi penderitaan. Maka pertanyaannya apakah dengan mengaplikasikan teknologi akan serta merta meningkatkan kebahagiaan pada masyarakat. Secara lansung tidak, namun teknologi memungkinkan pembuatan hukum dan penegakan yang lebih baik. Misalnya saja apakah kita bisa membentuk hukum dengan cepat sehingga perubahaan yang sangat cepat di dalam masyarakat dapat segera diatur, sebagaimana disadari bahwa hukum selalu terlambat. Proses legislasi yang panjang dan terseok-seok, daftar prolegnas yang tidak terkejar, tentu akan meningkatkan resiko kekosongan hukum dalam perkembangan zaman yang cepat. Kemudian kebijakan fiskal yang perlu dilihat apakah dampaknya seperti yang dimaksudkan, juga menjadi problematik yang terus dihadapi oleh legislator dan penegak hukum.  Dapatkah hal ini dipecahkan oleh teknologi. Sejauh ini, legislator, penegak hukum, advokat, dan komunitas hukum  menyadari perlu adanya alat dalam merancang dan menegakan hukum untuk membentuk hukum yang ideal. 

Beberapa teknologi lambat laun digunakan seperti automasi pada bidang birokrasi dan E-court. Teknologi ini pada dasarnya terbilang cukup membantu hukum untuk pindah dari kekunoannya. Meskipun membantu, namun ini belum cukup dalam mengembangkan hukum yang ideal. Sehingga, beberapa teknologi dipertimbangkan, salah satunya adalah   _Artificial Intelligence_. 


## Metode Kecerdasan Buatan yang sedang dikembangkan
_Artificial Intelligence_ atau kecerdasan buatan terbilang  masih baru. Saat ini Teknologi Kecerdasan buatan masih didefinikan terus menerus, seperti apakah kecerdasan ini perlu input dari manusia atau tidak sama sekali. Meskipun begitu, bila kecerdasan buatan dapat diaplikasikan untuk menciptakan hukum ideal dan menerjemahkan serta membantu penegakan hukum dapat terlaksana. Adapun jenis kecerdasan buatan yang digunakan ini adalah Natural Languange Processing atau NLP. NLP berfokus pada bagaimana komputer dapat memahami bagaimana manusia berkomunikasi, berbicara dan menulis. Tujuan NLP adalah untuk membantu komputer memahami bahasa manusia dengan cukup baik sehingga dapat berkomunikasi secara alami. Contoh dari NLP adalah seperti Alexa, Siri dan Okegoogle; Chatbots seperti simsimi; scanning text untuk melakukan ekstrak output seperti proses rekrutmen pada linkedin; grammarly dan autocomplete; dll.   

Terdapat 2 jenis kecerdasan buatan yang sedang dikembangkan untuk dipalikasikan pada hukum:  
1. Knowledge Guided: Symbol-based methods, metode ini digunakan untuk membuat teknologi seperti __Question Answering based on Law__, dan __text summarization__. Adapun metode yang digunakan adalah sebagai berikut:
		- Relation Extraction 
		- Information Extraction and Event timeline
		- Legal Element Extraction
		- Element Detection
2. Data Driven: Embending-Based methods, metode ini digunakan untuk membuat teknologi seperti __Judgment Prediction__  dan __Similar Case Matching__ untuk membantu hakin dalam menganalisi suatu perkara. Adapun metode yang digunakan adalah sebagai berikut: 
		- Concept Embedding 
		- Concept Knowledge 
		- Pretrained Language Model

## Kesulitan dan Permasalahan pada Natural Language Processing 
Permaslahan yang dihadapi saat ini untuk perkembangan teknologi NLP adalah: 
1. Sinonim; 
2. Ironi and sarkasme;
3. Ambiguitas; 
4. Error dalam teks atau perkataan;
5. Collonquialisms and slangs;
6. Bahasa negara atau daerah tertentu; 
7. Rendahnya kualitas data yang diterima;

## Solusi?

### Bahasa Baru
Komunikasi manusia sulit diterjemahkan secara lansung tanpa melihat terlebih dahulu konteks yang dimaksud, ditambah tidak semua bahasa memiliki karakteristik yang sama. Sehingga tidak ada jaminan penggunaa NLP oleh manusia dapat dimengerti oleh komputer secara sempurna. Maka hal yang memungkinkan dapat menyelesaikan permasalahan ini adalah dengan mengembangkan bahasa baru yang universal dimana dapat dimengerti oleh manusia dan komputer secara sederhana dan mudah. Penciptaan bahasa baru ini perlu menghilangkan hambatan-hambatan tersebut, sehingga bahasa baru ini perlu mengakomodir hal sebagai berikut: 
		- Bebas dari sarkasme, sinonim yang sulit, ironi, dan ungkapan/pribahasa;
		- Satu kalimat hanya dapat bermakna satu makna; 
		- Grammar yang dibuat perlu ;
		- Dapat diperluas;
		- Dan selebihnya bahasa ini perlu menghilangkan potensi hambatan pengapliasian NLP.   

Namun belum banyak data yang dapat dikumpulkan oleh para ilmuwan AI, akibat rendahnya kualitas data mentah yang perlu di latih untuk keperluan _Machine Learning_. Permasalahan inilah yang akan menjadi hambatan dalam pengaplikasian teknologi kecerdasan buatan pada sistem hukum yang modern. 

### Investasi Data dan Format data mentah

Maka dari itu tindakan ini perlu dilakukan segera oleh khususnya para instansi pemerintah terutama DPR, mahkamah agung dan mahkamah konstitusi. Hal ini dikarenakan rendah investasi yang ditempatkan pada bidang hukum sehingga hukum tertinggal jauh dari bidang lain seperti ekonomi dan sosial. Meskipun terdapatnya website satudata yang mengumpulkan data-data mentah instansi oleh pemerintah.  Namun kondisi saat ini masih belum ada terdapatnya integrasi antara lembaga-lembaga dan data mentah yang diambil.Adapun juga format data yang rutin digunakan oleh pemerintah adalah PDF. Hal ini sangatlah kontra-produktif untuk suatu data mentah, karena format PDF sulit untuk menjadi input dalam proses machine learning. Misalnya BPS cenderung menggunakan PDF, ketimbang penggunaan format JSON, CSV, dll. Format PDF pada dasarnya hanya diperuntukan untuk dibaca dan aksesbilitas format namun buruk bila diperuntukan untuk data mentah sebagaimana kita tahu bahwa PDF tidak dapat diubah. Maka dari itu project yang dilakukan pemerintah dalam membuat data mentah yang lebih baik lagi akan menjadi suatu kunci dalam memodernisasikan sistem hukum yang ada. 

Sehingga data mentah yang diperlukan untuk dilatih oleh machine learning, dapat terintegrasi dan dapat dilakukan selama banyak data yang terfilter dan disajikan dengan baik oleh pemerintah, dengan begini nantinya kita memiliki hasil dari data mentah yang berkualitas tinggi, untuk pengembangan program atau software yang dapat membantu masyarakat luas. Data mentah ini perlu menjadi open source yang dapat dimodifikasikan utuk kepentingan organisasi atau perusahaan. Sehingga semua orang dapat memanfaatkannya secara luas. Sehingga hukum dapat berkembang lebih jauh khususnya pada sisi penegakan yang baik dan perbaikan birokrasi.]]></content><author><name>raidendy</name></author><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hukum yang tertinggal]]></summary></entry></feed>