<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-10T02:49:29+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ray’s blog</title><subtitle>a personal blog
</subtitle><author><name>raidendy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Why I Day Dreaming A Lot Without Realizing It</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/why-i-day-dreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Day Dreaming A Lot Without Realizing It" /><published>2025-08-10T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/why-i-day-dreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/why-i-day-dreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="why-i-daydreaming-a-lot-without-realizing-it">Why I Daydreaming A Lot Without Realizing It.</h1>

<p>Date: 9 August 2025</p>

<p>Yes, the title is so long. But I want to talk regarding my tendency to have a personality toward Introvert and Intuition, because recently I have been discovered myself, that I have daydreams a lot, and I think this is related to the these function of my personality.</p>

<p>I have tested my personality from MBTI website such as 16personalities.com and paid personality test like Big Five of Traits from Jordan Peterson personality test website on understandmyself.com, also my DNA Test report. All of these tests and some repeated test that I took year after year, consistently tell that I’m an INTJ, which stands for Introvert, Intuition, Thinking, and Judging (Well sort of focused on Introvert and lend toward Intuition capability). This also aligned that I have specific trait in my genes that will make me become an Introvert and having intuition capability like ‘Introversion’, ‘Insighfulness’, ‘Creativity’, and  ‘Trading’ traits that says above average while other traits such as ‘Imagination’ labelled as Outstanding.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: While MBTI is very questionable personality test and people sometimes use it to strecthed into something like Zodiac. Nevertheless, I think it is good when we try to discuss specific traits using Carl Jung Personality Theory.</em></p>

<p>Introvert people is someone who dont get their energy from the external factor like Extrovert people (in a very limited definition).  It means that Introvert undervalue the thing outside of themself, which is what makes the introvert has a tendency and inclined toward more valuing to the internal factor of things which is themself.</p>

<p>While someone who has Intuition, Carl Jung defines the function as someone who perceives information unconsciously, often through patterns and possibilities that are not readily apparent to the senses or conscious thought. It means the ability to predict something.</p>

<p>In order to describe Introvert Intuition (Ni), we should also describe what is Sensing Extrovert (Se):</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Ni as a dominant function will lead the user to prioritize observing and taking in information, ultimately leading them to create an impression based off of this information. When making these observations, they won’t use details directly, rather they will try to look past the details themselves to see what the pattern structure is that the details are fitting into. This is one reason why Ni users tend to not remember a bunch of specific details, but rather the patterns that emerge as a result of the presented information. They want to be able to recognize certain markers to help them derive the sequence of events that are about to unfold, based on their internal database of past impressions. Because of this, they will prefer to observe first before taking any kind of action. They will want to forecast how things will play out before making a decision or acting. Because their extraverted function is in service to their dominant Ni, having some kind of structured decision will be secondary to making observations for the sake of collecting information.

Having Se as a lead function typically gives the user the urge to interact with the present current world around them. They are prone to boredom if they are forced to spend long periods of time theorizing or planning with no foreseeable way to act on the plans being made. These types are particularly drawn to act of doing and will have a desire to interact with whatever they are faced with in order to learn about it. When problem solving, Se dominants’ first instinct will be to play with the different options available to them in order to see what each thing does in order to form some kind of solution. These types will want to see how things physically change and will use that feedback to in order to inform their next move. While it’s not always extremely prominent, these types tend toward the mindset of living in the moment.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Source: <a href="https://practicaltyping.com/2021/10/25/the-functions-in-each-position-se-ni-ni-se/">Practical Typing</a></p>

<p>This 2 function of personality can be found in everyone else. Everyone can use it or have ability to use it. But for a certain people, it is how their mind usually works, and they more likely to think like their natural function, and not really familiar to use the other sense of their opposite function which in this case is Extrovert and Sensing.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Ni sees a web of information in their head so to speak. And their intuition helps them puzzle all pieces of the web together, narrowing down onto just one conclusion/idea. They live a lot in their heads, mulling over their ideas/conclusions. 

Se takes in information as it comes, day happens to them - Present focused (what is most relevant in that moment) - show someone else an experience - liking lots of stimulation and variety
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/mbti/comments/11e1x44/whats_the_difference_between_ne_and_ni/">Reddit</a></p>

<p>Jung said that daydreaming is natural activity of Ni People, which is very logical in that sense of their description. Daydreaming is a detachment of the consciousness, means that their mind like to wandering itself while doing something (sort of multitasking).</p>

<p>I do often daydreaming a lot during at work, in commuter, and while I’m riding. It is not thinking per say, thinking is different from daydreaming (sometimes we can mix that with thinking too), daydreaming… well you know is like living inside of your head and stay on that. Sometimes I forget what is the reality, this is also why after all this time, I dont think myself daydreaming, while the truth is I can’t see the difference between 2 realities. The mind speaks to me either give me some kind of imaginations like images or words, voices that emerge from within my mind. I do developed some kind of characters inside of my head, which later I called him “Mr. Check” to help me to tackle some internal or external issues.</p>

<p>When I read Carl Jung theory and people writing around his theory regarding Ni People, it sort of making me realize why I do what I do, and how stupidly I’m, for not aware that I have mistaken to think that my inner reality are also external reality. This mistake disabled my point of view to the both world.</p>

<p>Obviously It has some benefit too, of course, like skipping time, brainstroming, solving something (when combine it with thinking), but it will be bad because of detachment from the external reality itself and not using the Sensing function can be really bad when we are on something that require more intellectual capacity using Sensory organ like the eyes and hand that affecting on how we solve the problem. It Means that i lack the external data to use for my mind to predict what is the answers.</p>

<p>This is also explain why I’m good at pattern matching rather than remembering the detail of things.  I’m thinking something like which piece of puzzle in general that will be fit using such a shape, rather than focus on detail of the shape like using the puzzle side to match it. Sort of from abstract then to detail, rather than detail to abstract, or deductive vs inductive. This is the problem that I had.</p>

<p>But realizing this also comes with blessing. Like now I know, that I undervalue the external factor of myself, which is Sensing and Extrovert function. That sometimes i dont really care about my body and what other think. This is because I only appreciate what is my inner voice says not other people. This is also why I act so indifferent, or lack of purpose to tell about my findings or internal side of me to other people.</p>

<p>From this I also understand that why I choose to work as a legal especially a legal corporate which make sense, given my tendency to incline toward internal side of things. And why i will be focus on certain particular thing that i enjoy the most which connecting the dots within the dots and then like connecting on how legal work is almost the same as programming. The results is that i want to make a connection between legal and programming that can be applied at a certain level in a limited functionality and narrowed it down to specific thing like developing tools for legal. And this also explain why when it come to football, my favorite position is a Defensive Midfielder (CDM) rather than a striker or purely defender.</p>

<p>I also understand why i really like long project, that each smaller project is connected to the larger project and make it other project connected. I really like to stay on the problems.</p>

<p>But here is a catch, for people who dominant on Ni function which is their Se, they have a common problem:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Inferior Se is also playing into this type’s desire to look past the immediate details because the sensory in the present moment is being devalued. This also leads to their tendency to hesitate and not want to act immediately. Their lack of being present in the moment hinders their ability to react immediately and causes them to struggle with improvising. Things not going according to how they foresaw will very likely lead to them being disoriented and unsure of how to proceed. Inferior Se being exercised may lead these types to overindulge in some form of physical pleasure, like food, if not being properly regulated. In a more positive light, it will give these types a desire to travel or otherwise explore the sensory world around them. However, they will want to do so in a planned out and regulated manner as to not get overwhelmed.
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Source: <a href="https://practicaltyping.com/2021/10/25/the-functions-in-each-position-se-ni-ni-se/">Practical Typing</a></p>

<p>This means if I can slightly use more Sensory function, will make my Intuition function fully functioning because of the data that comes from Sensory function, that makes complete what is produce from my Intution using my inner reality to interact with external information.</p>

<p>By realizing this, now I know what need to be solved, which aligned on what Jung suggest that each person task is to learn the other side of themself or in this case my opposite function which is Sensing and to be more Extrovert, to balance out my our natural function and develop what is lack inside of me.</p>

<p>Also by realizing this, now I know what is truly my natural function that I can improve. For example my imagination is good, then by increasing the observing something  will lead to the betterness of my function even more, to make rich my internal world using mental image that i built during daydreaming. For example the Kim Jung Gi a korean artist, used to observe and draw a lot during his childhood, that can benefit him to draw the entire picture only using his mental image. I think He is the best example of someone who has a dominant Ni that also master his Se function.</p>

<p>Jung said that a truly functioning Ni people can act like what ‘Shaman’ position in tribes. Shaman predict the future and possess a healing factor to their tribe. This position can only be happen if Ni started to share their inner finding to the world.</p>

<p>I should truly see what I see, hear what I hear, and perceive something as they are. In order to be complete.</p>

<p><em>Watch materials</em>:
you should watch this if you are recongnize as a Ni: 
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DLANmpd-YFc
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i8o30eArkQA
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DmqFbgKWoao</p>]]></content><author><name>raidendy</name></author><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Daydreaming A Lot Without Realizing It.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mengukur Potensi Kecerdasan Buatan Pada Bidang Hukum</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mengukur-potensi-kecerdasan-buatan-pada-bidang-hukum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mengukur Potensi Kecerdasan Buatan Pada Bidang Hukum" /><published>2022-02-04T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2022-02-04T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mengukur-potensi-kecerdasan-buatan-pada-bidang-hukum</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mengukur-potensi-kecerdasan-buatan-pada-bidang-hukum.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="hukum-yang-tertinggal">Hukum yang tertinggal</h2>

<p>Sejauh perkembangan teknologi di abad ini, mulai dari bidang ekonomi, sosial, biologi, fisika, kedokteran, dan antariksa serta bidang keilmuwan lainnya. Namun terdapat bidang yang masih belum beranjak ketahap berikutnya dan kerap kali <em>old fashioned</em> yakni salah satunya adalah bidang <strong>hukum</strong>. Pertanyaannya mengapa demikian?</p>

<p>Kita dapat melihat bagaimana perekonomian sangat disokong oleh teknologi dengan meningkatnya efisiensi pabrik dan industri dalam penggunaan robot dan komputerisasi; Kemudian kehidupan manusia yang sulit terlepas dari teknologi internet dan sosial media; Penemuan antibiotik, vaksin dan teknologi kedokteran, memungkinkan terjadinya peningkatan standar usia manusia secara general; Penerbangan robot ke mars, dan Roket antariksa yang dapat digunakan kembali, memungkinkan peluang kolonisasi manusia di Mars. Namun dengan semua perkembangan teknologi, hukum jauh dari modernitas tersebut.</p>

<p>Kondisi sistem hukum dewasa ini, mulai dari proses pembuatan hukum hingga peradilan dan penegakannya, masih berjalan selayaknya sistem hukum yang dijalankan pada abad 19. Belum ada suatu perkembangan teknologi signifikan dalam peningkatan sistem hukum menuju tahap berikutnya.</p>

<h2 id="apakah-kita-memerlukan-itu-semua">Apakah kita memerlukan itu semua?</h2>

<p>Sebagai manusia, kemajuan akan menjadi titik penentuan meningkatnya kebahagian. Dalam pandangan hedonis dan utilitaran, kebahagiaan selalu menjadi pilihan utama dalam menentukan keputusan dan cara hidup demi mengurangi penderitaan. Maka pertanyaannya apakah dengan mengaplikasikan teknologi akan serta merta meningkatkan kebahagiaan pada masyarakat. Secara lansung tidak, namun teknologi memungkinkan pembuatan hukum dan penegakan yang lebih baik. Misalnya saja apakah kita bisa membentuk hukum dengan cepat sehingga perubahaan yang sangat cepat di dalam masyarakat dapat segera diatur, sebagaimana disadari bahwa hukum selalu terlambat. Proses legislasi yang panjang dan terseok-seok, daftar prolegnas yang tidak terkejar, tentu akan meningkatkan resiko kekosongan hukum dalam perkembangan zaman yang cepat. Kemudian kebijakan fiskal yang perlu dilihat apakah dampaknya seperti yang dimaksudkan, juga menjadi problematik yang terus dihadapi oleh legislator dan penegak hukum.  Dapatkah hal ini dipecahkan oleh teknologi. Sejauh ini, legislator, penegak hukum, advokat, dan komunitas hukum  menyadari perlu adanya alat dalam merancang dan menegakan hukum untuk membentuk hukum yang ideal.</p>

<p>Beberapa teknologi lambat laun digunakan seperti automasi pada bidang birokrasi dan E-court. Teknologi ini pada dasarnya terbilang cukup membantu hukum untuk pindah dari kekunoannya. Meskipun membantu, namun ini belum cukup dalam mengembangkan hukum yang ideal. Sehingga, beberapa teknologi dipertimbangkan, salah satunya adalah   <em>Artificial Intelligence</em>.</p>

<h2 id="metode-kecerdasan-buatan-yang-sedang-dikembangkan">Metode Kecerdasan Buatan yang sedang dikembangkan</h2>
<p><em>Artificial Intelligence</em> atau kecerdasan buatan terbilang  masih baru. Saat ini Teknologi Kecerdasan buatan masih didefinikan terus menerus, seperti apakah kecerdasan ini perlu input dari manusia atau tidak sama sekali. Meskipun begitu, bila kecerdasan buatan dapat diaplikasikan untuk menciptakan hukum ideal dan menerjemahkan serta membantu penegakan hukum dapat terlaksana. Adapun jenis kecerdasan buatan yang digunakan ini adalah Natural Languange Processing atau NLP. NLP berfokus pada bagaimana komputer dapat memahami bagaimana manusia berkomunikasi, berbicara dan menulis. Tujuan NLP adalah untuk membantu komputer memahami bahasa manusia dengan cukup baik sehingga dapat berkomunikasi secara alami. Contoh dari NLP adalah seperti Alexa, Siri dan Okegoogle; Chatbots seperti simsimi; scanning text untuk melakukan ekstrak output seperti proses rekrutmen pada linkedin; grammarly dan autocomplete; dll.</p>

<p>Terdapat 2 jenis kecerdasan buatan yang sedang dikembangkan untuk dipalikasikan pada hukum:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Knowledge Guided: Symbol-based methods, metode ini digunakan untuk membuat teknologi seperti <strong>Question Answering based on Law</strong>, dan <strong>text summarization</strong>. Adapun metode yang digunakan adalah sebagai berikut:
     - Relation Extraction 
     - Information Extraction and Event timeline
     - Legal Element Extraction
     - Element Detection</li>
  <li>Data Driven: Embending-Based methods, metode ini digunakan untuk membuat teknologi seperti <strong>Judgment Prediction</strong>  dan <strong>Similar Case Matching</strong> untuk membantu hakin dalam menganalisi suatu perkara. Adapun metode yang digunakan adalah sebagai berikut: 
     - Concept Embedding 
     - Concept Knowledge 
     - Pretrained Language Model</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="kesulitan-dan-permasalahan-pada-natural-language-processing">Kesulitan dan Permasalahan pada Natural Language Processing</h2>
<p>Permaslahan yang dihadapi saat ini untuk perkembangan teknologi NLP adalah:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Sinonim;</li>
  <li>Ironi and sarkasme;</li>
  <li>Ambiguitas;</li>
  <li>Error dalam teks atau perkataan;</li>
  <li>Collonquialisms and slangs;</li>
  <li>Bahasa negara atau daerah tertentu;</li>
  <li>Rendahnya kualitas data yang diterima;</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="solusi">Solusi?</h2>

<h3 id="bahasa-baru">Bahasa Baru</h3>
<p>Komunikasi manusia sulit diterjemahkan secara lansung tanpa melihat terlebih dahulu konteks yang dimaksud, ditambah tidak semua bahasa memiliki karakteristik yang sama. Sehingga tidak ada jaminan penggunaa NLP oleh manusia dapat dimengerti oleh komputer secara sempurna. Maka hal yang memungkinkan dapat menyelesaikan permasalahan ini adalah dengan mengembangkan bahasa baru yang universal dimana dapat dimengerti oleh manusia dan komputer secara sederhana dan mudah. Penciptaan bahasa baru ini perlu menghilangkan hambatan-hambatan tersebut, sehingga bahasa baru ini perlu mengakomodir hal sebagai berikut: 
		- Bebas dari sarkasme, sinonim yang sulit, ironi, dan ungkapan/pribahasa;
		- Satu kalimat hanya dapat bermakna satu makna; 
		- Grammar yang dibuat perlu ;
		- Dapat diperluas;
		- Dan selebihnya bahasa ini perlu menghilangkan potensi hambatan pengapliasian NLP.</p>

<p>Namun belum banyak data yang dapat dikumpulkan oleh para ilmuwan AI, akibat rendahnya kualitas data mentah yang perlu di latih untuk keperluan <em>Machine Learning</em>. Permasalahan inilah yang akan menjadi hambatan dalam pengaplikasian teknologi kecerdasan buatan pada sistem hukum yang modern.</p>

<h3 id="investasi-data-dan-format-data-mentah">Investasi Data dan Format data mentah</h3>

<p>Maka dari itu tindakan ini perlu dilakukan segera oleh khususnya para instansi pemerintah terutama DPR, mahkamah agung dan mahkamah konstitusi. Hal ini dikarenakan rendah investasi yang ditempatkan pada bidang hukum sehingga hukum tertinggal jauh dari bidang lain seperti ekonomi dan sosial. Meskipun terdapatnya website satudata yang mengumpulkan data-data mentah instansi oleh pemerintah.  Namun kondisi saat ini masih belum ada terdapatnya integrasi antara lembaga-lembaga dan data mentah yang diambil.Adapun juga format data yang rutin digunakan oleh pemerintah adalah PDF. Hal ini sangatlah kontra-produktif untuk suatu data mentah, karena format PDF sulit untuk menjadi input dalam proses machine learning. Misalnya BPS cenderung menggunakan PDF, ketimbang penggunaan format JSON, CSV, dll. Format PDF pada dasarnya hanya diperuntukan untuk dibaca dan aksesbilitas format namun buruk bila diperuntukan untuk data mentah sebagaimana kita tahu bahwa PDF tidak dapat diubah. Maka dari itu project yang dilakukan pemerintah dalam membuat data mentah yang lebih baik lagi akan menjadi suatu kunci dalam memodernisasikan sistem hukum yang ada.</p>

<p>Sehingga data mentah yang diperlukan untuk dilatih oleh machine learning, dapat terintegrasi dan dapat dilakukan selama banyak data yang terfilter dan disajikan dengan baik oleh pemerintah, dengan begini nantinya kita memiliki hasil dari data mentah yang berkualitas tinggi, untuk pengembangan program atau software yang dapat membantu masyarakat luas. Data mentah ini perlu menjadi open source yang dapat dimodifikasikan utuk kepentingan organisasi atau perusahaan. Sehingga semua orang dapat memanfaatkannya secara luas. Sehingga hukum dapat berkembang lebih jauh khususnya pada sisi penegakan yang baik dan perbaikan birokrasi.</p>]]></content><author><name>raidendy</name></author><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hukum yang tertinggal]]></summary></entry></feed>